Now in the previous video, we created the layouts for our two new activities.
Agora, no vdeo anterior, criamos os layouts para nossas duas novas atividades.
And in this video we're going to add the code to make those activities work.
E neste vdeo vamos adicionar o cdigo para fazer essas atividades funcionarem.
Now, we haven't yet got a class for the standalone activity, because we're adding the activity manually
Agora, ainda no temos uma aula para a atividade autnoma, porque estamos adicionando a atividade manualmente em
instead of using the wizard.
vez de usar o assistente.
So when I open the project pane if it's not open,
Ento, quando eu abro o painel do
and then come on down to the actual package which is under the Java folder, right click, click on new and select
projeto se ele no estiver aberto, e ento deso para o pacote real que est sob a pasta Java, clique
Kotlin File/Class, and we're going to call this one StandaloneActivity,
com o boto direito, clique em novo e selecione Arquivo / Classe Kotlin, e ns chamaremos
and under Kind, we're going to select Class instead of File, and click on OK.
esse StandaloneActivity e sob Kind, vamos selecionar Class em vez de File e clicar em OK.
Now this class is going to extend the AppcompatActivity class,
Agora esta classe vai estender a classe AppcompatActivity, ento
so I'm going to type after the class name, space colon.
eu vou digitar aps o nome da classe, espao clon.
And I'm going to type Appc, and that should be enough to bring up this list of classes, and I'm going to choose
E eu vou digitar Appc, e isso deve ser o suficiente para trazer essa lista de classes, e vou
AppCompatActivity from that list for the superclass, and I need to add parentheses on the end of that line.
escolher AppCompatActivity a partir dessa lista para a superclasse, e eu preciso adicionar parnteses no final dessa linha.
Now we also want to implement an interface, and unlike Java, in Kotlin there's no implements keyword.
Agora tambm queremos implementar uma interface e, ao contrrio do Java, no Kotlin, no h nenhuma palavra-chave de implementos.
You just separate the class from the subsequent interfaces using a comma.
Voc apenas separa a classe das interfaces subseqentes usando uma vrgula.
So what I'm going to do is type a comma, then after the comma I'm going to type in onClick, and we
Ento o que eu vou fazer  digitar uma vrgula, depois da vrgula eu vou digitar onClick, e ns chegamos na caixa
get to the interface's box as you can see there, and we've got a couple of options there.
da interface como voc pode ver l, e ns temos algumas opes l.
Now, we need to implement the view dot onClickListener, so make sure you select the right one from the
Agora, precisamos implementar o view dot onClickListener, portanto, certifique-se
list. It should be already selected and you can see in my case the first one is selected, and IntelliSense
de selecionar o correto da lista. Ele j deve estar selecionado e voc pode ver no meu caso que o
is very useful here, but you do really have to pay attention to what you're doing.
primeiro est selecionado, e o IntelliSense  muito til aqui, mas voc realmente precisa prestar ateno ao que est fazendo.
So we're not creating a dialogue interface so we don't want this second one,
Ento no estamos criando uma interface de dilogo, ento no queremos esta
so make sure you choose the correct one and press enter, and that adds that line for us.
segunda, ento escolha a correta e pressione enter, e isso adiciona essa linha para ns.
Now that's our basic class created, and there's no functions added at the moment.
Agora essa  a nossa classe bsica criada, e no h funes adicionadas no momento.
It is easy to do so, we just need to position the cursor inside the class,
fcil fazer isso, s precisamos posicionar o cursor dentro
in other words, inside the left and right curly braces, and use control O to choose the onCreate function
da classe, em outras palavras, dentro das chaves esquerda e direita, e usar o controle O
from the list. So control O, and you can just type the first few letters, onCreate, and there's onCreate, press enter,
para escolher a funo onCreate da lista. Ento, controle O, e voc pode digitar as primeiras letras, onCreate,
and that implements it for us, and I'm just going to make an extra line of code there, or put
e h onCreate, pressione enter, e isso implementa para ns, e eu vou fazer uma linha extra
an extra line there. Now when we used the wizard to generate the YouTubeActivity for us,
de cdigo l, ou colocar uma linha extra h. Agora, quando usamos o assistente para gerar o YouTubeActivity
the onCreate code was slightly different to what was generated here.
para ns, o cdigo onCreate foi um pouco diferente do que foi gerado aqui.
Now hopefully Google will have sorted this out and made them consistent, by the time you watch this.
Agora, esperamos que o Google tenha resolvido isso e os tenha tornado consistentes, no momento em que voc assistir a isso.
But don't worry if you get slightly different code
Mas no se preocupe se voc pegar um cdigo
as I have, because I'm going to be changing this code in a minute anyway, and you'll be able to make yours
um pouco diferente, porque eu vou estar mudando esse cdigo em um minuto de qualquer maneira, e voc ser capaz
match if necessary.
de fazer a sua correspondncia, se necessrio.
Now we've still got an error here at the moment, and that's relating to the fact that we haven't implemented
Agora ainda temos um erro aqui no momento, e isso est relacionado ao
the onClick function yet, which is a required function for the onClickListener interface.
fato de que ainda no implementamos a funo onClick, que  uma funo necessria para a interface onClickListener.
So let's put that right first.
Ento vamos colocar isso em primeiro lugar.
So we're going to put a blank line after the onCreate function.
Ento, vamos colocar uma linha em branco aps a funo onCreate.
This time I'm going to do a control I to get the implements method's dialogue, and
Desta vez eu vou fazer um controle para obter o dilogo do mtodo implements, e
I'm going to choose onClick there which is the only option that can be selected, and press enter.
vou escolher onClick l que  a nica opo que pode ser selecionada, e tecle enter.
Alright so at this point that's now cleared the error.
Tudo bem ento neste momento que est agora apagou o erro.
So what is this interface though we're implementing, and why are we doing it.
Ento, qual  essa interface que estamos implementando e por que estamos fazendo isso?
Well before I explain that, let's go back and add the code to the onCreate method because it'll make
Bem, antes de explicar isso, vamos voltar e adicionar o cdigo ao mtodo onCreate porque ele far mais sentido
more sense when you see the code in there.
quando voc vir o cdigo l.
So I'm going to start by leaving that super.onCreate line on line 14 as is, and on the next
Ento eu vou comear deixando esse super. onCreate linha na linha 14 como est, e
line I'm going to do a setContentView, and it's going to be R.layout dot,
na prxima linha vou fazer um setContentView, e vai ser R. layout dot, vamos escolher nosso layout
we're going to choose our activity standalone layout, activity_standalone. OK,
autnomo de atividade, activity_standalone. OK, prxima
next line we're going to do btnPlayVideo.setOnClickListener, parentheses, this, and we're going to do the same
linha, vamos fazer btnPlayVideo. setOnClickListener, parnteses, isto e ns vamos fazer o
for the btnPlaylist, btnPlaylist.setOnClickListener,
mesmo para o btnPlaylist, btnPlaylist. setOnClickListener, isso, e eu fiz um L
this, and I did a capital L there, it should be a lower case l, that's better.
maisculo, deveria ser um minsculo l, melhor.
Alright so that's the onCreate function, and hopefully you should recognize that code, because it's almost
Tudo bem, ento essa  a funo onCreate, e esperamos que voc reconhea esse cdigo, porque  quase idntico
identical to the way we've been finding buttons in the layout, and setting them onClickListener so that
ao modo como encontramos os botes no layout e os definimos onClickListener para
we can respond to the buttons being clicked. And Android Studio's added the synthetic import for us as
que possamos responder aos botes que esto sendo clicados. E o Android Studio adicionou a importao sinttica para ns,
you can see there, on line 6.
como voc pode ver l, na linha 6.
Now there's a slight difference in the way that we've set the click listener this time though.
Agora h uma pequena diferena na forma como definimos o ouvinte de cliques desta vez.
So I'm going to comment these two lines out for now, and review the two different ways that we've done
Ento, vou comentar essas duas linhas por enquanto e revisar as duas maneiras diferentes como
this previously. Let's go ahead and do that.
fizemos isso anteriormente. Vamos em frente e faa isso.
Now the first way is btnPlayVideo.setOnClickListener, in parentheses it was object colon View
Agora a primeira maneira  btnPlayVideo. setOnClickListener, entre parnteses, era objeto dois pontos View dot Em
dot On Click Listener, and then we need our left and right
Click Listener, e depois precisamos das
curly braces, then we did an override control O, choosing onClick.
nossas chaves esquerda e direita, ento fizemos um override control O, escolhendo onClick.
So that was the first, that's the approach we used in the button counter app in section 5,
Ento essa foi a primeira, essa  a abordagem que usamos no aplicativo contador de botes na seo
and we can also implement that a different way, using a lambda expression. So I'm going to comment that one out, and
5, e tambm podemos implementar isso de uma maneira diferente, usando uma expresso lambda. Ento, vou comentar isso, e a outra maneira
the other way of doing it, as I mentioned, was a lambda expression.
de faz-lo, como mencionei, foi uma expresso lambda.
So that's btnPlayVideo.setOnClickListener,
Ento  btnPlayVideo. setOnClickListener e, em
and then in parentheses, view.OnClickListener, press enter there, and within the left and right curly braces we'll
seguida, entre parnteses, exibir. OnClickListener, aperte enter l, e dentro das chaves esquerda e direita vamos
put v then an arrow token, press enter, and then we're going to do our TODO, so TODO, we can actually copy
colocar v ento um token de seta, aperte enter, e ento ns vamos fazer o nosso TODO, ento
that entire line so let's just do that. Copy that line and then we'll uncomment it,
TODO, ns podemos realmente copiar toda a linha ento vamos apenas faa isso. Copie essa linha e depois descomente-a e
and that's now valid. Now that's a lot tidier because we don't need all that boilerplate code in colon,
isso  vlido agora. Agora isso  muito mais arrumado porque no precisamos de todo esse cdigo padro
and this is the code I'm referring to here, this override code on line 22.
em dois-pontos, e este  o cdigo a que estou me referindo aqui, esse cdigo de substituio na linha 22.
Now that's fine if you're only using the listener with a single button. Typing all that in for each button's
Agora tudo bem se voc estiver usando apenas o ouvinte com um nico boto. Digitar tudo isso para cada boto
a bit tedious though,
um pouco entediante,
so what we can do is we can assign it to a variable, and use the same variable then for each button.
ento o que podemos fazer  atribuir a uma varivel e usar a mesma varivel para cada boto.
So I've commented out that first bit of code out, and let's review the approach we use, which is very similar
Ento, eu comentei o primeiro cdigo, e vamos rever a abordagem que usamos,
to what I've typed in the calculator app. Alright so I'll comment that out that, and the other thing we could've done, is we can assign
que  muito semelhante ao que eu digitei no aplicativo da calculadora. Tudo bem, ento vou comentar isso, e a outra coisa que poderamos ter feito,  que
it to a variable and use the same variable for each button.
podemos atribu-lo a uma varivel e usar a mesma varivel para cada boto.
So we could do something like val listener equals view.OnClickListener, then we need our left and right curly brace, our braces,
Ento, poderamos fazer algo como val ouvinte  igual a viso. OnClickListener, ento ns precisamos de nossa chave direita e
and within the left and right curly braces, v arrow token, then we can paste in the code for the TODO, like
esquerda, nossas chaves, e dentro das chaves esquerda e direita, v smbolo de seta, ento podemos colar
so, and clean that up. And then we could do btnPlayVideo.setOnClickListener, listener, and btn
o cdigo para o TODO, assim, e limpar isso. E ento poderamos fazer btnPlayVideo. setOnClickListener, listener e
Playlist.setOnClickListener, listener.
btn Playlist. setOnClickListener, ouvinte.
So here we basically created a new onClickListener object, and assign it to a variable,
Ento, basicamente, criamos um novo objeto onClickListener e o atribumos a uma varivel,
and we can then pass that variable to the setOnClickListener method of as many buttons as we need.
e podemos passar essa varivel para o mtodo setOnClickListener de quantos botes precisarmos.
Now what that code does is create an anonymous inner class, and assign an instance of that to a variable.
Agora, o que esse cdigo faz  criar uma classe interna annima e atribuir uma instncia a uma varivel.
And that's the way we did it when we wanted to assign the same listener to several buttons in the calculator
E foi assim que fizemos quando quisemos atribuir o mesmo ouvinte a vrios botes no aplicativo
app in section 6.
da calculadora na seo 6.
Now obviously the code had to work out which button was tapped, to do something different for each one,
Agora, obviamente, o cdigo tinha que descobrir qual boto era tocado, para fazer algo diferente para cada um,
but this does save having to create a new listener for each button.
mas isso poupa ter que criar um novo ouvinte para cada boto.
Now a third approach we can take is to make our activity a listener.
Agora, uma terceira abordagem que podemos tomar  tornar nossa atividade um ouvinte.
Now if the activity implements the onClickListener interface, it can be passed whenever the onClickListener's
Agora, se a atividade implementar a interface onClickListener, ela poder ser passada sempre que as
implementation's needed.
implementaes do onClickListener forem necessrias.
That's what I did originally when I passed this up here on lines 18 and 19, to
Foi o que eu fiz originalmente quando passei isto aqui nas linhas
the button's setOnClickListener method, function. As long as our activity satisfies the interface,
18 e 19, para a funo setOnClickListener do boto. Contanto que nossa atividade satisfaa a interface, em
so in other words it implements the onClick function, then we can use an instance of our activity whenever our
outras palavras, ela implementa a funo onClick, ento podemos usar uma instncia de nossa
listener's needed. So I'm going to comment out at all this other code, leaving in just the original set dot
atividade sempre que o nosso ouvinte precisar. Ento, vou comentar todo esse
OnClickListeners, and uncomment these two. So all approaches here, all three approaches, pretty much do the same thing.
outro cdigo, deixando apenas o conjunto original OnClickListeners e descomentei esses dois. Ento, todas as abordagens aqui, todas as trs abordagens, praticamente fazem a mesma coisa.
The advantage of the way we're using it now though, is that it moves the onClick code out of onCreate, and
A vantagem da maneira como estamos usando agora,  que ele move o cdigo onClick para fora do onCreate, e isso pode tornar as
this can make things more readable when the onClick function's quite long. It's not sort of messing
coisas mais legveis quando a funo onClick  bastante longa. No  uma baguna da funo
up the onCreate function in other words. So which approach should you use
onCreate em outras palavras. Ento, qual abordagem
here? Well it's really up to you as to which of the approaches you take, when you've got multiple buttons using
voc deve usar aqui? Bem, cabe a voc decidir qual das abordagens voc
the same listener. If there's a lot of code in the onClick function, then implementing the interface and
adotar, quando tiver vrios botes usando o mesmo ouvinte. Se houver muito cdigo na funo onClick, implementar a interface e usar
using this can make the code more readable, as we're about to do.
isso pode tornar o cdigo mais legvel, como estamos prestes a fazer.
And it also means that you can use instances of the class as a listener elsewhere in your code, to assign
E isso tambm significa que voc pode usar instncias da classe como ouvinte em outro lugar em seu
it to buttons and other activities.
cdigo, para atribu-la a botes e outras atividades.
Now that's maybe not something you'd do with a class that extends activity or AppcompatActivity, but
Isso talvez no seja algo que voc faria com uma classe que estende a atividade ou
it may be useful in other classes.
AppcompatActivity, mas pode ser til em outras classes.
Alright, so we've got a listener attached to both of our buttons now, so we now need to write the code
Certo, ento temos um ouvinte ligado aos dois botes agora, ento agora precisamos escrever o
to get it to do something.
cdigo para fazer algo.
Now what we want to do is launch Google's standalone player with the ID of a video to play, or the
Agora, o que queremos fazer  lanar o player autnomo do Google com o ID de um vdeo para reproduzir ou
ID of a playlist, and when we click the button it'll start the YouTube Player, almost as if you'd launched
o ID de uma playlist, e quando clicamos no boto, ele inicia o player do YouTube, quase como se
it yourself from the phone's launch screen. Now it's slightly different to launching it manually, because we can also
voc o tivesse lanado na tela de incio do telefone. Agora  um pouco diferente de lan-lo manualmente, porque tambm podemos dizer qual
tell it which video to start playing, but apart from that it's the same. Alright so the code is quite simple, so
vdeo comear a reproduzir, mas fora isso  o mesmo. Tudo bem, ento o cdigo  bem simples,
I'm going to type it in then explain what's going on. So let's go down to the onClick function, and
ento vou digit-lo e explicar o que est acontecendo. Ento vamos para a funo onClick, e
we're going to remove this TODO now that because we are implementing it. And I'm going to start by typing val intent
vamos remover esse TODO agora porque estamos implementando. E eu vou comear digitando
equals when, then parentheses view.id, and our left and right curly braces,
val intent equals quando, ento parnteses view. id, e nossas chaves esquerda e direita, e precisamos mudar
and we need to change the name that was assigned. It's not really the best name there, p0,
o nome que foi atribudo. No  realmente o
we'll change that to view, and you're going to get rid of the question mark for now.
melhor nome l, p0, vamos mudar isso para ver, e voc vai se livrar do ponto de interrogao por agora.
So within the code block for when, we're going to do R.id.btnPlayVideo arrow token, and that's going to be
Ento, dentro do bloco de cdigo para quando, vamos fazer o R. identidade. token de seta btnPlayVideo, e
YouTube, with a capital T, StandalonePlayer.createVideoIntent, then parentheses, and
ser o YouTube, com um T autnomo de capital. createVideoIntent, em seguida, parnteses, e vamos digitar 'this' como o
we're going type 'this' as the first argument, comma space getString, then parentheses R.string dot
primeiro argumento, getString de espao de vrgula, ento parnteses R. string dot GOOGLE_API_KEY fechar vrgulas do
GOOGLE_API_KEY closing parentheses comma YOUTUBE VIDEO_ID, or YOUTUBE_VIDEO
YOUTUBE VIDEO_ID, ou YOUTUBE_VIDEO _ID, depois adicionar nosso direito,
_ID, then add our right, our closing parentheses. Alright so that's the first one.
nossos parnteses de fechamento. Tudo bem, ento esse  o primeiro.
Second one, we're going to do something very similar but this time for a playlist,
Segundo, vamos fazer algo muito parecido, mas
R.id.btnPlaylist arrow token, it's going to be YouTubeStandalonePlayer
desta vez para uma playlist, R. identidade. token de seta btnPlaylist, ser YouTubeStandalonePlayer,
dot, this time it's createPlaylistIntent, parentheses, and we'll start with this on the first line, comma space, and we'll
desta vez  createPlaylistIntent, parnteses, e comearemos com isso na primeira linha, espao de vrgula, e faremos uma string
do you a get string again, parentheses R.string dot
de novo, parnteses R. string ponto GOOGLE_API_KEY
GOOGLE_API_KEY again, parentheses comma space.
novamente, parnteses espao de vrgula.
And then we'll do a YOUTUBE_PLAYLIST this time, YOUTUBE_PLAYIST in that line there, and then we're just going to add an else,
E, em seguida, faremos um YOUTUBE_PLAYLIST desta vez, YOUTUBE_PLAYIST nessa linha, e depois
basically right down here, else arrow token again, and
adicionaremos outra, basicamente aqui, outra seta novamente,
we're going to throw IllegalArgumentException, and we'll put "Undefined button clicked". OK, then outside of
e vamos lanar IllegalArgumentException, e ns vou colocar "boto indefinido clicado". OK, ento fora desse bloco de cdigo
that code block we're going to put startActivity intent. Alright so to start an activity,
vamos colocar a inteno startActivity. Tudo bem, ento, para comear uma atividade, usamos a funo
we use the start activity function and we pass it something called an intent.
de atividade de incio e passamos algo chamado de inteno.
So the code checks to see which button was tapped to call the onClick function, then sets the data for
Portanto, o cdigo verifica se o boto foi pressionado para chamar a funo onClick e, em seguida, define os
an intent before calling startActivity.
dados para uma inteno antes de chamar startActivity.
Now we can use the playlist ID that we got earlier to play the playlist, and the video ID that we've
Agora, podemos usar o ID da playlist que recebemos anteriormente para reproduzir a playlist e o ID do
already defined in the YouTubeActivity class, to play a single video.
vdeo que j definimos na classe YouTubeActivity para reproduzir um nico vdeo.
In both cases, we need to pass and use our Google API key,
Em ambos os casos, precisamos passar e usar nossa chave de API do
and if you recall, both the ID's were declared as top level constants in YouTubeActivity, which means
Google e, se voc se lembrar, ambas as IDs foram declaradas como constantes de nvel superior em YouTubeActivity, o que significa que podemos
we can use them without having to qualify them with a YouTubeActivity class name.
us-las sem precisar classific-las com um nome de classe YouTubeActivity.
So in other words we added the definition above the class definition.
Ento, em outras palavras, adicionamos a definio acima da definio da classe.
Now once you know what an intent is, the code's fairly easy to understand.
Agora, uma vez que voc sabe qual  a inteno, o cdigo  bastante fcil de entender.
So let's actually have a look at the Google documentation for intents.
Ento, vamos dar uma olhada na documentao do Google para intenes.
Alright, so we need to know a bit more about what an intent is, because once we actually figure that out you'll
Tudo bem, ento precisamos saber um pouco mais sobre o que  uma inteno, porque, uma vez que
find the code is pretty straightforward to understand.
descobrimos isso, voc descobrir que o cdigo  bastante simples de entender.
So let's work on that in the next video.
Ento vamos trabalhar nisso no prximo vdeo.